Konvitz, Milton Personal Correspondence /4241
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Milton Konvitz Personal Correspondence
1941-2003
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Konvitz, Milton
/4241
2.5 cubic feet
2.5 linear ft.
Correspondence.
8056841
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, January 12, 2004
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, October 05, 2016
Biographical / Historical
March 12, 1908-September 5, 2003 Milton Konvitz, a Cornell University faculty member and authority on constitutional and labor law, and civil and human rights, died Sept. 5 at the age of 95. Konvitz was a founding faculty member in the School of Industrial and Labor Relations from 1946 until his retirement in 1973. He was also a professor in Cornell's Law School. Konvitz is perhaps best known for his American Ideals course, which he taught to more than 8,000 students over the course of his career, never giving the same lecture twice. "I saw the U.S. Constitution as it has been interpreted as a magnificent depository of our ideals, both individual and social," he said. His course exposed students to the great intellectual thinkers and philosophers throughout history whose writings had shaped those ideals. They included Sophocles, whose play Antigone is Cornell's New Student Reading Project this year. One student he influenced was U.S. Supreme Court Justice Ruth Bader Ginsburg, Cornell Class of 1954, who considers him a mentor. At Cornell Konvitz also was a founder of the university's Department of Near Eastern Studies and Program of Jewish Studies. "I felt it was essential for a college interested in the humanities not to leave out Hebrew language and literature," he said. "And the knowledge of Jewish history, which began 4,000 years ago and has contributed to civilization no less than Greek, Roman or English history, is important to today's students-Jewish and non-Jewish." He often hosted students at his Ithaca home and helped start the first Kosher dining option at Cornell, Young Israel House. In addition, for nearly 30 years he directed the Liberian Codification Project, which drew up the official body of statutory laws that is still in force in the Republic of Liberia today, despite the current political upheaval there. Konvitz also edited the opinions of Liberia's Supreme Court and received the Grand Band of the Order of the Star of Africa, the highest award given to foreigners, as well as an honorary degree from the University of Liberia, one of seven honorary degrees he received in his lifetime. Active as a scholar and writer until his death, he wrote books and articles on American constitutional law that won him wide recognition and were cited in U.S. Supreme Court opinions. Among his nine books is Fundamental Liberties of a Free People: Religion, Speech, Press, Assembly, which was republished earlier this year with an expanded introduction by him that is strongly critical of the Rehnquist Supreme Court. Other books include A Century of Civil Rights (1983) and Judaism and Human Rights (2nd ed. 2001). He also edited a dozen volumes, including two on American philosopher Ralph Waldo Emerson, whose thinking shaped his views. One Emersonian idea he absorbed was that readers give life to books, which Konvitz recast as follows: "It is in their hearing that students bring life to the words, the thoughts, the teacher." Konvitz was born in Safed, Palestine (now Israel ), in 1908, the son of a rabbi. He immigrated to the United States in 1915 and became a naturalized citizen in 1926. He received a bachelor's degree in 1929 and a law degree in 1930, both from New York University, and a Ph.D. in philosophy from Cornell in 1933. Before joining Cornell's faculty, he was one of three assistant general counsels to Thurgood Marshall at the NAACP Legal Defense Fund for three years. He is survived by his wife, Mary, of Oakhurst, N.J.; a brother, Phillip, of Elberon, N.J.; a son and daughter-in- law, Josef and Isa, of Paris, France; and two grandsons, Eli and Ezra. Josef Konvitz, who grew up in Ithaca, is now an official at the Organization for Economic Co-operation and Development.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: /4261m: "Some Aspects of Negro-Jewish Relationships in Detroit, Michigan" Manuscript /4085: Milton R. Konvitz Additional Papers /4039 AV: Milton R. Konvitz American Ideals Lectures Audio-Visual Materials /4039 L: Milton R. Konvitz Liberian Codification Project /3033: Milton R. Konvitz Liberian Project Files /4039: Milton R. Konvitz Papers /4039 B: Milton R. Konvitz Additional Papers /4220m: Milton Konvitz Additional Papers /4242 AV: Milton Konvitz Memorial Service Audio-Visual Materials /4039 AV: Milton R. Konvitz American Ideals Lectures Audio-Visual Materials /4315 G: ILR School Milton Konvitz Memorial Lecture Posters
Arrangement
Series I. Personal Correspondence
Series II. Publications
Konvitz, Milton R. (Milton Ridvas), 1908-2003; New York State School of Industrial and Labor Relations
8056841
- Series I. Personal Correspondence
  - Abramsky, Chimera, 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Adams, James Luther, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Scope and Contents
    11/7/1989
  - American Ideals Course (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Cohen, Morris Raphael (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Cohn, Justice Haim, 1971-1974 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Contributors to Konvitz chair, 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    7/21/97 - 9/23/98
  - Cornell chair special letters, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    April - May 1998
  - Cornell University correspondence, 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Cornell University presidents, 1946-2003 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    6/24/46 - 4/15/03
  - Dedication of Konvitz chair, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    5/18/1998
  - Eisensten, Rabbi Ira, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    11/4/1996
  - Fundamental Liberties of a Free People, 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    7/12/01 - 9/17/02
  - Glass, Rabbi Scott, 1990-2003 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    8/14/1990 - 3/20/03
  - Goldfarb, Rabbi Morris, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Gussman, Herbert and Roseline, 1991-1998 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Hook, Sidney and Anne Hook, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    1/30/1989
  - Journal of Law and Religion, 1993-2001 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    1/12/1993 - 3/12/2001
  - Judaism and Human Rights, 1999-2002 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    August 1999 - January 2002
  - Kallen, H. M. (son David Kallen), 1997-2002 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Kampelman, Max, 1989-2001 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    10/11/1989 - 6/18/2001
  - Liberia, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Materials regarding Konvitz chair dedication, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    5/9/1998 - 5/18/1998
  - Midstream. Minutes of Board Meetings, 1988-1996 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    3/24/1988 - 5/30/1996
  - Midstream. Konvitz reviews, 1987-2001 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    October 1987 - April 2001
  - Midstream. 1 of 2, 1989-1997 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    6/89 - 4 /97
  - Midstream. 2 of 2, 1990-2001 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    11/6/1990 - 4/10/2001
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1984-1998 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    10/22/1984 - 4/21/1998
  - Miscellaneous Letters, 1 of 4, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    March - July 1999
  - Miscellaneous Letters, 2 of 4, 1989-1991 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    October 1989 - October 1991
  - Miscellaneous Letters, 3 of 4, 1941-2000 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    9/12/41 - 8/7/00
  - Robinson, Greg, 1996-1998 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    4/3/1996 - 10/5/1998
  - Rutgers - Nine American Jewish Thinkers, 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Rutgers - Fundamental Rights, 1999-2001 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Supreme Court Justices., 1990-2001 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    May 1990 - April 2001
  - Szekely, Yoram., 1993-1995 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Students, 1990-2000 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Tanner, Harold and Stephen Weiss, 1997-2002 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    5/1/1997 - 12/3/2002
  - Adams, James Luther, 1972-1993 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    1/10/1972 - 5/28/1993
  - Cohn, Justice Haim, 1991-2001 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    9/29/1991 - 11/25/2001
  - Cornell Jewish Studies. 1 of 2., 1987-1998 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    12/10/1987 - 11/5/1998
  - Cornell Jewish Studies. 2 of 2., 1990-2003 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    9/28/1990 - 4/22/2003
  - Gaulkin, Judge Edward. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Goldfarb, Rabbi Morris. 1 of 2., 2001-2002 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    10/8/01 - 8/12/02
  - Goldfarb, Rabbi Morris. 2 of 2., 1990-2001 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    1/12/1990 - 6/3/2001
  - Gotesky, Rubin., 1997 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Grade, Mrs. Chaim, 1980-1995 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    1/7/1980 - 12/15/1995
  - Grade, Inna Hecker., 1993-1998 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    4/93 - 5/98
  - Hebrew Culture Foundation., 1987-1995 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    5/22/1987 - 6/13/1995
  - Hertzberg, Arthur; Hannah Arendt; Frank Rhodes; Alfred Gottschalk; Norman Lamm, 1970-1990 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    12/31/1970 - 4/23/1990
  - Jewish Studies, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    January - April 2003
  - Jung, Rabbi Leo (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Letter from Student, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    3/21/2001
  - Levy, Harold. 1 of 3, 1999-2001 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    8/7/99 - 1/17/2001
  - Levy, Harold. 2 of 3, 1991-1996 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    1/30/1991 - 2/11/1996
  - Levy, Harold. 3 of 3, 1989-2002 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    11/26/1989 - 5/31/2002
  - Major Donors to the Konvitz professorship (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Memorial papers by Konvitz, 1983-1990 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    9/12/1983 - 3/25/1990
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1987-1993 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    8/6/1987 - 7/8/1993
  - Miscellaneous letters. 1 of 2, 1966-2000 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    2/28/1966 - 2/9/2000
  - Miscellaneous letters, 2 of 2 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Personal papers. Milton Konvitz, 1945-1990 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    3/10/1945 - 9/24/1990
  - Rackman, Rabbi Emanuel, 1 of 2, 1990-1998 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Rackman, Rabbi Emanuel, 2 of 2, 1999-2003 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    1/22/99 - 4/9/03
  - Rutgers - General Correspondence., 1999-2003 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    6/12/99 - 4/30/03
  - Saloveitchik, Rabbi Joseph B., 1950-1999 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    11/9/50 - 8/8/99
  - Supreme Court Justices, 1990-2003 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    7/3/90 - 6/11/03
  - Vicious Circle, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    May-86
  - Encyclopedia Judaica Articles, 1980-1986 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    7/17/80 - 7/30/86
  - Goldstein, Morris, 1995-2003 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    5/12/95 - 3/5/03
  - Hertzberg, Arthur, 1990-2002 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    6/30/90 - 10/16/02
  - Lamm, Rabbi Norman, 1989-2001 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    9/6/89 - 3/28/01
  - Letters from Cornell faculty, 1991-2003 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    1/9/91 - 6/4/03
  - Miscellaneous letters, 1 of 2, 1992-1997 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Miscellaneous letters, 2 of 2, 1988-2003 (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Series II. Publications
  - 1954 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    One publication with notes to Prof. Konvitz
  - 1964 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Two publications with notes to Prof. Konvitz
  - 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Four publications with notes to Prof. Konvitz
  - 1973-1978 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - 1981 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - 1990-1995 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Six publications with notes to Prof. Konvitz. One is in Hebrew.
  - 2000-2001 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Two publications with notes to Prof. Konvitz, both are from the Berman Memorial Lecture Series, Queens College, by Emanuel Rackman. Also includes a greeting card and circular letter.